All right, folks, let's begin.
So today I'm gonna be talking about the
four golden signals of AI coding agents
basically applying the last 20 years of
SRE thinking on production systems to the
new production system that's running on
everyone's laptop, my laptop, your laptop.
It's AI coding assistants,
Claude, Codex, et cetera.
So before that, I'm just gonna
give a brief intro about myself.
So I'm currently founding two companies.
One is for developing software for
other software engineers and people
in the engineering community, and the
other is for non-software engineers.
And as you can probably guess
CodeTelemetry is the one
for the engineering space.
The goal of CodeTelemetry is to
provide observability into AI
coding assistants, similar to what
I'm going to be discussing today.
And Mirror Panel is a company I
started with a very close friend
of mine that I studied marketing
with at McGill University way
back in the, in around 2010.
The goal of that company is to provide
synthetic panel research to companies
that are interested in doing market
research and advertising positioning.
So how did I get here?
So from around 2009 to 2020, I
was doing application engineering,
infrastructure engineering.
Initially I was working as a
full stack developer, sort of
freelance, and then eventually I
ended up doing AWS stuff at Adobe.
And then around 2020, I started
working on site reliability
engineering at Capital One.
I pivoted to a company called Kustomer
that was then acquired by Meta, where I
was working as a principal AI engineer.
Then I went back to site reliability
at JPMorgan, but at that point, the
intersection between AI and site
reliability engineering started to
converge because I was working more
on things that are starting to get
similar to AI with self-healing
systems, so finding ways to
resolve incidents programmatically.
And then more recently at Mastercard,
I was working on gen AI platform
engineering specifically around how do
we optimize our coding assistant usage.
Okay, so let's dive into the talk.
So where does this come from?
Many of you are probably familiar with
the Google SRE four golden signals.
I'm just gonna go over it
briefly as a refresher.
Google SRE four golden signals, it
came out in twenty sixteen, around the
time when I started working at Adobe.
And basically what it seeks to establish
is that if you're monitoring these
four things you can say that you're
beginning to understand the state of
your systems in production and can
make qualified decisions about how it's
performing and if it's reliable or not.
So just gonna go through these quickly.
So latency is how long work takes.
So you can think about this as how long
does a request take to go from one of
your client's web browser through a load
balancer into your server to the database
and then back down to the browser again.
In real life, you could think about this
as if we're imagining that our system
is a bridge, it's how long does it take
for a car to drive over that bridge?
Traffic is how much work is arriving.
The number of requests that are going
through that server, the number of
people that are using your website
and how does that compare to your SLA
for how much traffic can you handle?
In bridge terminology, that's
how many cars are driving over
the bridge per day or per hour.
And is that too many cars?
Errors.
So this is my favorite one is five
xx errors against a load balancer.
That's just meat and potatoes error
monitoring in four golden signals.
I guess in bridge terminology, this
would be how often the bridge collapses.
Thankfully, that's pretty much never.
Or maybe car accidents on a bridge.
Maybe not though.
Maybe that's not the bridge's
fault, that's the car's fault.
Interesting.
We can think about that analogy later.
And saturation, how close
you are to the limit.
This is the one that I struggle
with cognitively the most.
The classic example for how to
measure this in a production system
is CPU utilization, so of that
server that's handling the traffic.
But we'll get into that a
little bit more very soon.
So the, the premise of this talk, your
coding agent is a production system which
is maybe hard to wrap our heads around
because we've always thought of our local
environment as the true dev environment.
It-- You've heard the expression, "Oh, it
works in dev," or, "It works in local."
So why should we think about the
coding agent as a production system
instead of a local environment?
It increasingly is running unattended.
The-- Anthropic just changed the, the
defaults for this to run in auto mode
last week in the end of August 2026.
And runs against your real repository,
runs for a long time, and increasingly
it runs in the cloud as well.
It doesn't even run in
your local environment.
So just to defend this in
a little bit more depth.
Some of you may already agree with
this, but just to… Bear with me here.
So these are five things that we
already sort, know how to monitor
in production, but these are aspects
of AI coding assistants that make
them production environments.
So they call external services.
So there's the, the model APIs.
It's hitting the Anthropic
API, the OpenAI API.
Maybe it's hitting Azure Foundry or AWS
Bedrock if you're self-hosting the LLMs.
It's hitting MCP servers, so maybe
these are dev tool MCP servers or
your actual applications MCP server.
There are shells that can run all sorts
of arbitrary API requests that download
things from npm or from pip or from
Artifactory, et cetera, et cetera.
There's test runners tools like Signat
or Blacksmith, where you can spin
up cloud environments to run tests.
Those-- So those are more external
services that your ag- that
your agent could be hitting.
And here's a big one.
It constr- it consumes
constrained resources.
So we're increasing, increasingly
discovering that tokens aren't free.
And in, in fact, it's worse than that.
They're massively subsidized.
So as of September 2026, we're probably
going to look back on today one year
from now and think, "Ah, those were the
good days when AI coding was cheap."
It's going to get more expensive.
Looking at things like how
much tokens are we using?
How are we consuming our context window?
What's our rate limit?
These are becoming production
problems And retry failure.
So basically the coding assistant
shares the behavior of production
where it will autonomously try to
fix problems on its own which could
basically become a a cycle problem.
I'm forgetting the name of it.
Don't worry about that.
So yes.
What else?
Maintain state.
So a context window will
degrade as it fills.
This is similar to production in that
you'll… if you're not cycling your
servers out, you'll see that the behavior
of your applications will change from when
you first launched them to one week from
they were-- when they were launched or
two months from when they were launched.
And finally, they im--
produce consequential output.
So this is things like your commits or
the pull requests that the agents post.
Sometimes the agents have direct
access to development environments,
hopefully not your production
environment, where it's doing
migrations and deploy config settings.
So This is, this slide
is meant to be a joke.
So this is the operator blind spot.
So on the left, you have
the four golden signals.
A service that you operate, you
should expect to see, your latency,
your traffic rate, an amazing
point oh four percent error rate.
That's awesome.
Saturation looks a little
high, sixty-one percent.
Maybe we want a little headroom.
That's awesome.
But then if you compare those four golden
signals to what probably you can see out
of the box with Claude or Codex, with
the observability tools that they give
you you can see, oh, an agent started
forty-seven minutes ago, but we don't
really know anything else about it.
And I think this slide is
actually, when I think about
it, being a little bit generous.
We likely actually only know
that some tokens were spent
sometime in the last hour.
We don't even know that in, that
it was from an agent that was
launched forty-seven minutes ago.
Maybe it was multiple agents.
That's, that much is not clear.
So what do we do about this?
So I'm going to itemize the different
things that we can monitor in agent
sessions to bring our observability
up to a hundred percent of the Google
SRE golden signals so that we can feel
confident that we really know what's
happening in an AI coding assistant.
I'm not gonna go over
the column on the left.
That's the production stuff that we all
know and love and are all familiar with.
I'm just gonna go over the right column.
So for traffic it's things like how many
human prompts are we getting through our
coding assistants, the quantity of tool
calls and the variety of tool calls, the
quantity of tokens that those sessions
are producing, and the types of file
edits that are happening in the sessions.
And all that needs to be contextualized
by session with session metadata
Second category is errors.
This one's really interesting to
me, and we're gonna dive deeper
into this in a little bit because
it's deceptively complicated.
So things that you can look
at are reported tool failures,
failed tests, and reverted edits.
And some of you might be already
thinking about wait a minute.
How's that gonna work?"
We're gonna talk about that.
Number three latency.
So this, this one's pretty
easy to wrap your head around.
So it's basically from the time
a session begins to different
check marks in the SDLC cycle.
So basically the, from the first
prompt to when the AI coding
assistant started editing files.
And then the second checkpoint is when
it produced tests that all passed.
And then the third checkpoint is
when we got a reviewable change.
These are your latency metrics.
This is similar to things like from
the browser to the load balancer,
from the load balancer to the server,
from the server to the database.
It's the same premise, measuring latency
at different checkpoints through a system.
And then group number
four, we've got saturation.
So this is things like context pressure.
So basically how much of the million
token count or whatever the the token
size limit is for models when you're
watching this in the future, I hope.
Things like rate limits.
So if you're using a Claude or Codex
subscription model, that's something
that you need to bear in mind.
But it's also rate limits of the
downstream systems that you depend on.
So if you are oops spinning
up dev servers, there's a rate
limit on the number of dev
servers you can spin up per day.
Another saturation mesh- metric
like concurrency is interesting in
that if you are editing, if you have
multiple agent sessions running in
parallel and they're all editing the
same file, what's going to happen?
When you open a PR, there's
going to be conflicts.
So concurrency is another element of
saturation that we need to monitor.
Okay, so that's all well and good.
Let's start to dive into the details of
this and how it's maybe a little bit more
complicated than I've described so far.
So we'll start with an example of
something from pre-AI coding assistants,
and it's a classic SRE question.
Is a 4XX status code an error?
So if you get a 404 message,
is that something that we
need to monitor and alert on?
Is that a problem?
And the answer to that
question is, it depends.
So if the 404 message is from
the homepage of your website,
then yeah that's a big problem.
That means that the clients of
the business that you're operating
can't can't see what you're selling.
But if the 404 error is from some
random nested page from some sort
of web crawler that's just trying to
guess for things that's not an error.
So 404, normal behavior, but sometimes
an indicator of incorrectness.
And the same thing
applies to agent sessions.
So if you see a tool call that
failed and when I say failed, I mean
returned an exit code that isn't
exit zero in Bash is that an error?
And the answer to that question
is probably not, actually.
So when we're talking about measuring tool
call failures, what does that even mean?
So if… for example, if maybe your agent
is doing the initial exploration of the
code base and is grepping for a particular
code pattern as a memory-efficient way
to identify where certain functions exist
across your code base, That would retur-
that could potentially return a non-exit a
non-zero exit code, which is a good thing.
That means the agent is learning.
So what do we do with that insight?
So bear with me here.
This is, I promise, the busiest
slide in this presentation.
So I'm gonna go over a specific
session that I've analyzed, and
these are some of the UIs within code
telemetry that I have for understanding
what's happening with a session.
So in this case, the, the task
that we're working on is linear
task ELL Elliot fifty-one.
We're working on bringing our task size
limit for… Or sorry, we're bringing
the task size API latency to within
its two-second targets, one of the,
one of the features I'm developing.
Okay.
So on the left, what,
what's actually happening?
Throughout the timeline, we can
see that as the agent is spinning
up, it's looking at the… It's
running its repo layout probe.
It's looking at GitHub workflows to
understand, okay, how is this code going
to be evaluated once we publish it?
Some environment probes happening, and
then it runs into its first failure.
It's running an LS
command of node modules.
And then if you look in the upper
right, we can see that no such
file or directory was found.
So I think for many developers
that's pretty obvious for us.
What does that mean?
It means, oh, we have to run NPM install.
Awesome.
I guess I can start working
on this half an hour from now.
But we can see that for this probe,
the, the ultimate answer is that
eventually eight seconds later I
guess it was recovering from a cache
NPM CI was okay eight seconds later.
So in this case, that, that wasn't a
failure because it ultimately recovered.
That's not something that
we would want to report on.
However, if we look further down in the
task context, there's a message that
says, "This needs a benchmark against
real data," which I have not run.
So basically what Claude or Codex is
saying in this case is that we weren't
actually able to run a benchmark against
the original acceptance criteria of the
task, that code was changed, but we don't
actually know with evidence that we've
met our task size API latency goals.
Correctness should be judged against
the outcome, not necessarily tool
status ev- or tool status evidence can
be, can inform correctness but isn't
necessarily the right verdict Okay.
To just clarify that last sentence,
which I know is a little confusing.
I confused myself.
How is correctness established?
Task intent what the agent was asked to
achieve, so 200 or two-second latency.
A relevant check, so do we have a
specific test or benchmark or some sort of
dependency check to evaluate that intent?
And then three, an observed result.
So are we actually able to capture
that relevant check through
some sort of telemetry system?
What did the sy-system actually do that?
And then finally, four, some
sort of comparison mechanism.
So the degree to which that
original task intent was captured.
So if the agent in that previous session
had run an integration test and said, "Oh,
looks like the the new latency is around
a second and a half," we could say that
we met the goal of that previous task
Okay, so this is one
of my favorite slides.
So I mentioned the challenge a couple
of slides back around looking at tool
call failures I… Sorry, there's
a little bit of noise outside.
Hopefully, you guys don't hear that.
So failure patterns in agent sessions.
So this is a prescription for how we
can evaluate tool call failures in a way
that's actually meaningful instead of just
a whole bunch of noise of false positives.
So the first one is the retry
loop, and there's a couple of
different ways that this manifests.
But imagine this cycle,
you've probably seen it.
An agent makes some edits to some code.
It runs a test.
The tests fail.
It says, "Ah, I need to make
more edits." And then it makes
those edits, runs more tests.
The tests fail.
And you might be thinking, "Oh, Elliot,
that's test-driven development. That's
how software engineers have been writing
code for a long time." And you'd be right.
But the problem is that as humans, we
can usually remember the first test when
we're-- or the first edit and think I've
tried this before, and it didn't work.
I need to think more critically about
the changes that I'm making instead of
just continuing to make random edits
here and there, copy and pasting from
Stack Overflow and running tests," right?
Oops, I accidentally went too far.
So that's the retry loop.
That's something that we can
monitor is the depth of recursive
testing for an AI coding assistant.
We also have things like
repeated edits with no tests.
So imagine you see, ah, auth.typescript
was edited seven times with a bunch of
thinking happening in between, but no test
was actually run at any phase in that.
It's the, the opposite of the
retry loop, where maybe there's not
enough TDD, test-driven development,
being baked into the edit process.
So it's just guessing at these edits.
Number three is tool fallback.
I think this one is pretty interesting.
I think we're gonna go over some
of the runbooks that we can follow
for what to do when we run into
these errors in a slide or two.
So tool fallback.
So the, the goal of MCP in the context
of Model Context Protocol, in the context
of AI coding assistants, is to reduce
the amount of tool use in an assistant.
So basically to shortcut a bunch of token
use and tool usage into a single MCP call.
But sometimes MCP fails, and
when that happens, the agent
will fall back to bash commands.
So that's something that you can
monitor and then improve upon.
We also have things like
spend without progress.
So this is when maybe three hundred
tokens are spent two files are changed,
but then no tests were run, and then
even worse, no pull request was opened.
We all have Just a graveyard of branches
on our laptop of things that we tried.
Maybe they didn't work out
and we forgot about them.
And this is normally fine, but if
the original task was something
that we really care about…
Oh, sorry about that noise.
I'm just gonna let that pass for a second.
If the original task is something
that we really care about, then
spend without progress is a problem.
If it's something our clients
are waiting for then that's
something that we need to fix.
And then finally, review rework.
So here on the slide,
it's expressed in minutes.
I think it's more interesting to think
about this as a different type of
retry loop than necessarily minutes,
although that's important too.
But starting to get outside the
scope of code observability.
So if you think about the, the life
cycle that I've described, where the
end of latency is maybe the agent's
opened a PR, there's actually another
whole section of coding latency that's
going to happen that comes from a human
or some other agent reviewing the pull
request and your coding agent then
going and resolving that review process.
So the quantity of review checks
and the quantity of additional
coding sessions is another failure
pattern that you can monitor for.
So just to summarize are
retries producing evidence?
And just to clarify everything
from that last slide.
So we can say that an AI coding
assistant is converging when tests
are failing, it's editing things,
it's encountering different errors,
and then ultimately succeeding.
But it's stuck if it is repeatedly
encountering the same type of
failure after the same edits.
So what do we do with
all this information?
And I think if you're like me and
are interested in building products
to improve developer experience
this will excite you, right?
This is-- you can use this data to
justify to the businesses that you work
for the really awesome projects that you
want to build to save everybody time.
So what are some things that you can
do when you encounter these errors?
So for that node modules example maybe
there's something that you can change
with your environment bootstrap.
Maybe there's a startup image that
all of the laptops should have that
have those node modules baked into
place so that you're not losing
time in every session installing
and losing tokens checking for that.
On the flip side, maybe
everything is succeeding.
It's a great problem to have but maybe
that's because you're running every
single session with Fable five dot one,
and you're spending twenty x what you
should be on all of your coding projects.
So maybe you can tweak some of the model
defaults to or maybe the effort levels
of those models to improve your outcomes.
I think there's a, an interesting
sizing project there that's similar
to what we see in production with
right-sizing our databases and EC2
instance sizes, and et cetera, et cetera.
Modifying your agent dot md, your
skills dot md files, I think here's
where you would try to bake in hey,
use this particular testing pattern
instead of reinventing the wheel.
Every now and then, you'll be on
Reddit or Hacker News or something
and-- or your friend down the road,
and they'll recommend an agent
dot md or skills dot md change.
This is a way to sanity check were those
changes effective or are we just taking
shots in the dark guessing at different
improvements for AI coding assistance.
And then number four is basically we're--
if these tools continue to improve
the way that they're doing, we're all
basically architects, not engineers.
And one of the things we can do is
improve the way that we're doing
spec-driven development and improve
the way that we're doing planning.
So if we're seeing that context is
frequently getting overloaded, that
means that we need to resize our
work and reorganize the tasks that
we're handing to coding assistants.
Or if we're seeing that there are
frequent conflicts in our PRs, maybe
that means we need to take a, a sprint
to just work on code organization.
Is there a way that we could restructure
the code so that we can improve the
concurrency of our AI coding edits so
that they don't bump into one another?
So- This is not an
exhaustive list obviously.
It's just there to get
the creative juices going.
And with that, I'll close out s- with this
with this thought that in production, we
never-- we as the software engineering
community, site reliability engineers
likely the people who are listening to
this talk, we didn't make production
reliable by making software stop failing.
We made failure observable.
And if we can do that same thing
for coding assistants, then we can
become experts in how to operate
them in a way that will really
transform the productivity and
quality of the software that we build.
So with that, I will just add
at the end here that this is
something that I'm hope you…
hope it comes off that I'm
clearly passionate about.
If these are problems that
you're working on solving as
well, please reach out to me.
I'm happy to collaborate with you.
You can find my email in the
second slide where I introduce
myself in the lower left.
Thank you, and have a wonderful day.